[Music]
you can't tell how someone feels just by
looking at them or what they share
online to the outside world our lives
may look perfect even if in reality they
aren't I'm always worrying about doing
well at school and with the end-of-year
test coming up I'm not sure how much
longer I can cope my thoughts swarm
around my head sometimes keeping me up
all night some days it's just all too
much and I feel like I'm lost in space
when I did badly on one of my tests I
just about kept it together until I got
home then I broke down crying in front
of my mum she listened for a bit and
then she told me that just like physical
health we all have mental health it's
our feelings our thinking our emotions
and our moods she then said that feeling
down anger and stress is a normal part
of life just like it's normal to feel
happy confident and carefree sometimes
we all have positive and negative
emotions that come and go based on
what's happening around us these are
everyday feelings good mental health
means experiencing negative emotions
it's not always about being happy
mum can relate to the themes of stress
when mom suggested I take a break from
everything and do something I enjoy
actually took her advice so I made
myself a hot chocolates not good often
adieu then watched a film and you know
what afterwards I felt so much better
mom should take her own advice most of
us only ever shared the good things we
don't like to share how we really feel
every morning when I wake up negative
thoughts streamed through my head
getting out of bed and pretending I'm
okay
takes all the energy I have as the day
goes on the negative thoughts turn from
a stream into a river the water rushes
through my head so loudly it's hard to
concentrate in lessons and some days
it's so bad it feels like a waterfall
that trying to pull me over the edge
everything is so overwhelming I didn't
think my friends would understand if I
told them how down I was feeling but
when Sasha opened up to me about how
stress she was feeling I told her I
wasn't sure how to bring up how I've
been feeling so I started by saying that
I didn't feel like myself just her
listening made me feel like she
understood
she told me some things that have helped
her so I tried them too but it didn't
make much of a difference even when I
tried to be around my friends I felt
alone the things I used to enjoy weren't
fun anymore
I was really worried about Andre I'm not
sure what to do he was quiet and wasn't
hanging out with us like he used to so I
asked our head of year for some advice
he suggested I get Andre to speak to him
since his negative feelings weren't
going away I didn't want to speak to our
head of year but I also didn't want to
keep feeling so down so I went he said
that sometimes we have overwhelming
feelings that can be more intense than
our everyday feelings these feelings
hang around for a long time and changed
the way we feel think and behave they
can stop us doing what we want to in
life that's what I was going through he
also said that if were physically unwell
we let people know we asked for help it
should be no different with mental
health sometimes our overwhelming
feelings are brought on because of
things in our life sometimes they happen
for no reason at all after hearing this
I felt much less alone and it felt good
to talk scientists have found exercise
can help when you're feeling low so
ahead of year encouraged me to sign up
to the school football club which Sasha
was already in I still have days when
the river is there but now I'm beginning
to understand my mental health I'm
learning how to cope ahead every year
reminded me that my friends my family
teachers and lots of others at school
are there to help just as much as he is
I had no idea that people around me
could be so understanding and while it's
not always easy to talk about my mental
health the person I'm talking to you
might be able to help if you don't feel
like talking that's fine
you could try writing sports reading art
music playing with your pet whatever
makes you feel better
if you're the person someone talks to
when they're struggling just listen with
no pressure or judgments you don't have
to have the answer if you feel unsure
about anything you can speak to a
trusted adult talking about mental
health doesn't have to be difficult
after all is something we all have
[Music]
you